A Guide to the Papers of Jackson Davis, 1910-1947
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Jackson Davis 1910-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3072-b
This collection contains ca. 100 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection of material related to Jackson Davis, and his work on education in the South, was made a gift to the Library by Sally Guy Brown and Helen Langhorne of Alexandria, Virginia, on February 11, 1999.
Alternative Form
Both the 1911 and the 1913 travel diaries are available as electronic texts.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 100 items, 1911-1999, pertaining to Jackson Davis and his work with the General Education Board, the State Board of Education, and education in Africa. Included are letters, typescripts, papers, photographs, printed, and travel journals.
General Education Board papers include a 1942 statement concerning automobile travel and the use of gasoline by Davis as associate director of the General Education Board and a 1946 address by Davis given at the unveiling of the bust of Booker T. Washington. There is also an undated fragment of a letter discussing the missionaries in Africa and various places, including the Belgian Congo; Las Palmas, Canary Islands; and, Treetown, Sierra Leone. There are statements, ca. 1940, on counties in Alabama.
Letters, 1942-1945, from Jackson Davis discuss activities in South America and Africa. A letter of October 27, 1942, from Bogota, Colombia, mentions activities and gives brief descriptions of Bogota and Lima, Peru. A November 8, 1944 letter, from Lagos, Nigeria, mentions Dr. [John] Bugher's study of the jungle type of yellow fever and plans to go to the Belgian Congo. A letter of November 19, 1944, from Leopoldville, Congo Belge, mentions activities; plans to travel to Stanleyville; the death of [John Stewart] Bryan and the reelection of [Franklin Delano] Roosevelt; and, describes Leopoldville and its situation on Stanley Pool. A December 4, 1944 letter, from Leopoldville, concerns mission, medical, and educational work in the heart of Africa, including villages and towns of Stanleyville, Yakusu, and Kindu.
News from Africa letters from Jackson Davis discuss activities in Africa on an official basis. Letters of November 11 and December 12, 1944, from Leopoldville, Congo Belge, discuss war-time conditions in Liberia and at Achimata College; activities and meetings with various people, including African-American journalist [Thomas White] Young (1908-1967), officials at Achimata College, John Bugher, and the United States Vice Consul. The latter letter discusses visits to Kisantu, Sona Bata, and Kimpese in regard to educational, medical, and agricultural facilities and programs; visits to Stanleyville, Yakusu, Ineac (the government's main Agricultural Experimental Station), Tunda, and Wembo Nyama. A January 7, 1945 letter, from Zaria, Nigeria, discusses visits to Duala, Bangwa, Baffousam, N'Diki, Dshang, Abeokuta, Ibadan, and Zaria. A letter of January 25, 1945, from Lagos, Nigeria, discusses visits to Zaria, Kano, Arochuku (Scottish Mission), Akwa Training School; several native rulers; and, refers to the influence of pagan customs and the Moslem system of "Purdah."
There are also letters of condolence to Robert D. Calkins, Associate Director of the General Education Board, from various college presidents and officials and missionary councils. Correspondents include P. Tulane Atkinson, Harry Clemons, Virginius Dabney, Spright Dowell, Joseph Dupuy Eggleston, Francis Pendleton Gaines, Ivey F[oreman] Lewis, E. G. McGehee, Jr., Fred T. Mitchell, John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., Anson Phelps Stokes, E. G. Swem, and Dean Acheson.
There are photographs, 1940-1943, of Jackson Davis; General Education Board members; Jackson Davis Elementary School; Davis grave markers; natives in Africa; Davis with Charles E. Diehl and Sir William Beveridge; and others.
Travel journals, 1911 and 1913, kept by Jackson Davis, chiefly describe his tours and activities through towns in Virginia and North Carolina and discuss the education of African-Americans. Entries of January 1 to June 7, 1911 consist of minimal personal entries. During mid-June, Davis travels to the Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute and St. Paul's School in Petersburg; Hampton Institute and the Trade School and Dow Science Building; and the University of Virginia summer school registration. He discusses the significance of training mind and will through hand. A visit to Hampton [Institute] Summer School provides a discussion on building an African-American school outside of Hampton. During June 23-26, Davis attends conferences in Montreat, North Carolina. He mentions students in "Negro Life classes"; comments on John Little's method of teaching African-Americans; describes his view of the climb of "Graybeard" with Charles Edward Stowe (1850-1934); and, mentions work on the Committee on Negro Association with George Foster Peabody (1852-1938), Samuel Chiles Mitchell (1864-1948), John Little, and [Willis Duke] Weatherford (1875- ). From June 27 to July 4, Davis is in Charlottesville, meeting with [Hollis Burke] Frissel (1851-1917), [Charles Gilmore] Maphis (1865-1938), K[ary] C[admus] Davis (1867-1936), [Charles William] Kent (1860-1917), and [Bruce Ryburn] Payne (1874-1937). He refers to Frissell's comments on improving the economic conditions of African-Americans and Kent's suggestion that there should be "negro trustees for the colored schools." He also provides a quote concerning Thomas Jefferson's scheme for the education of the people of Virginia and describes the pageant of the Virginia Delegation. On July 5-6, Davis visited Virginia Union University in Richmond, meeting with its president [George Rice] Hovey (1860-1943) and [Algernon Bertrand] Chandler, Jr. (1870-1928). He refers to Hovey's comments on "the idea of higher work." On July 7-8, Davis met with Colonel [Samuel Harden] Church (1858-1943); he refers to the Virginia Plan and other improvement plans and the improvement of summer school each year. On July 18, there is the Rural Life Conference in Charlottesville; comments are made on topics covered by [Hollis Burke] Frissell, Caroline P. Davis, Edwin Mims (1872-1959), and [Bruce Ryburn] Payne and on his own speech on "The Negro in Country Life." Davis' next visits were to Hampton, where he met with [Joseph Dupuy] Eggleston (1867-1953) and attended the Negro Conference; Harrisonburg, and Manassas, where he met with L[eslie]; P[inckney] Hill (1880-1960), discussing personnel and tuition. During July 26 to 29, Davis went to St. Louis, Missouri to speak to the National Association of Teachers "in colored schools." He describes the land from Cincinnati to St. Louis, refers to feelings of discrimination in the distribution of funds and to comments made by T. C. Walker, J[ohn]; M[anuel] Gandy (1870- ), and others. In early August, Davis writes about the Superintendents' Conference in Farmville, and later discussing comments made by Eggleston on the work of examiners and their role in having measures enacted by the State Board of Education. On August 23-24, he is with the Appomattox Association in session Baptist Church and discusses schools and colleges doing great work but that county funds are being drained. In late August, Davis visits various family vegetable gardens in Halifax County, commenting on the vegetables, cultivation, and canning. On September 2, Davis had a conference with [Charles Gilmore] Maphis and others in regard to colored schools; he lists the points agreed upon and mentions Julia Ferguson and Josephine Pride. On September 7, Davis met in Richmond with [Willis Duke] Weatherford, John Stewart Bryan (1871-1944), and R. M. Smith. There were visits to homes, vegetable gardens, and tobacco fields in Nottoway County; he comments that African-Americans are more prosperous here. During September, he also made visits to homes, farms, and schoolhouses in Dixondale and Gloucester. There are statistics on property owned by African-Americans, criminal records, and lists of Baptists churches and preachers in Centralia, Chesterfield County. Late September, in South Boston, canned goods were being set up for the canning exhibit at Suggs and Jones Store; and, in Cumberland, there was an exhibit of tomatoes and canned goods by African-Americans. During October, Davis visited schools in Hampton, Elizabeth City County, Brunswick County, Henrico, and Caroline County. There are negative comments about conditions in Brunswick County, including children being infected with hookworm and lands being neglected. In Charlottesville, there was a conference with B. C. Caldwell, Johnson, Everett, Shelton, and Josephine Pride. On October 16, Davis visited Virginia Randolph and discusses briefly her plan of industrial work. Following a visit to Caroline County, he mentions Bowling Green Industrial Academy, Mattie Holmes, Virginia Union University in Richmond, [George Rice] Hovey, and colored churches. In Petersburg, he attended sessions of the Colored Bible Study Institute and mentions Lottie Jefferson and the canning exhibit. From October 23-27, Davis was in Gloucester, and comments extensively on a Mr. Folkes, a minister, born to a colored wet nurse; comments on visits to schools (white and colored) and a meeting of teachers. Topics discussed in the meeting were health, morality, home improvement, economic improvement, industrial work, and rural development. From November 4-9, Davis was in Hampton, where he had conferences with Wallace Buttrick (1853-1926), Wickliffe Rose (1862-1931), [Joseph Dupuy] Eggleston, and [Hollis Burke Frissell]. He mentions several points, including Colonel Church's resignation and the poor condition of Union State School as well as speaking on school and farm demonstration. While in Burkeville November 10-14, Davis mentions Reaumur Coleman Stearnes (1866-1945) and his philosophic address. In Honaker, November 17-18, Davis met at Honaker School with principal H. C. Williams and mentions Dorothy Mitchell, the Russell County Teachers Association, Fugate, the need for trained teachers, and Mr. Swain, principal of Agricultural High School in Lebanon. On November 22, he mentions Farmers' Warehouse, tobacco acreage and sales, prosperous farmers growing tobacco, the Farmers Cooperative Guano Company, and a visit to Blackstone Colored High School. On November 22, in Richmond, he mentions Health Day, Arthur Wright, Chester Colored School, Lottie Jefferson, and a meeting of the State Board. Notes from November 28-30 discuss the Education Conference, the meeting of the Executive Committee Cooperative of the Education Association, a proposal to ask the Southern Education Board for a larger amount this year, and DeJarnett's Colored League. He also comments on addresses by [Joseph Dupuy] Eggleston and Miss Jessie Fields of Page County, Iowa on rural schools. During December, Davis traveled to Williamsburg, Kenbridge, Richmond, and Hampton. On December 11, he comments on Miss [E.G.] Agnew's idea of combining home and garden work with the school curriculum and on the discussion of the Board of Examiners. There is a memorandum including a list of books read near the end of the journal.
Davis' 1913 travel journal includes entries discussing his visits to schools and counties in Virginia from January through October. On January 3, he visited Caroline County, where he met Superintendent John Washington; he describes the Dawn school building. On January 10, in Williamsburg, he discusses a meeting of teachers in five peninsula counties for the purpose of organizing a school fair. While in the office, Davis refers to various people and topics: [Reaumur Coleman] Stearnes, [Wallace] Buttrick; [Charles Gilmore] Maphis, [ ] Robinson, and [James Hardy] Dillard (1856-1940); an offer of the position of secretary and his decision to stay with current work; the need for field men; a meeting on arrangements for the Conference of Education in the South next April; [Joseph Leonard] Jarman's (1867-1947) comments on Virginia Military Institute; and, plans for Health Day. From January 15-17, he visited Hampton, Dinwiddie, and Prince Edward County, and mentions a visit to Shellbanks with Dr. Phenix, the condition of schools in Dinwiddie, meeting P. Tulane Atkinson at Farmville, and the condition of schools in Felden. In Hampton, February 1-3, Davis discusses the Founder's Day Exercises and meeting all colored supervisors and demonstrators on one side and white supervisors in front; he mentions Rhea Scott, Margaret McCane, Sue Cleaton, Lottie Jefferson, E. G. Agnew, Virginia Randolph, and Norah Bocock. During mid-February, he mentions visits to Henrico Industrial School, Greenwood Mountain Road School, Pole Road Industrial School; needing two women in Hampton to help John B. Pierce supervise the canning; and, a meeting of colored teachers at Centralia, Chesterfield County. On March 4-5, he mentions visits in Goochland to the Court House, Miller Colored School, and Beaver Dam Colored School; meeting in Henrico with J.L. Sibley, supervisor of Negro Rural Schools in Alabama; a visit to Jeter School and Industrial School; and, meeting Virginia Randolph. On March 6, he describes visits to rural schools in Middlesex, and mentions Saluda High School, the Exhibit of Colored Schools, Sibley's lecture on work in the Philippines, and a proposition for a central school. On March 9, there is mention of the work of industrial teachers and demonstrators. Jackson Davis made no entries from March 10 to May 31, with the exception of a reference to the purchase of lot 4 in the block of Ginter Park on May 22. During June, there are references to plans for supervisors in Hampton; the Disputanta High School graduation; speaking at "Colored Chatauqna" at Front Royal; industrial work in Front Royal schools; [reverends] J. B. Dinkins and M. E. Church; and, the annual celebration of the Alumni Association in Williamsburg. During early July, there are references to St. Paul's Summer School; school and farm demonstration work; Thyne Institute in Chase City; White Normal; and, the disreputable conditions of "The Ridge," a slum near Boydton. On July 11, Davis mentions people working toward certification at Virginia Union University and Estelle B. Wingo studying to be supervisor for Amelia County. On July 15-16, there are references to the Rural Life Conferences and Horticultural Society meeting at the University [of Virginia]. Visits to Manassas and Madison follow; summer school inspections, a meeting of stockholders of Robinson Cove Orchard, and Normal [Institute] are mentioned. Davis also comments on Miss Caroline Preston Davis revealing that the Civic Club paid the salary of the science teachers at the Negro School in Charlottesville and that she had obtained a black teacher a job as a maid at the Summer Institute at the University of Virginia so the woman could observe a class there. There are scattered notes from July 19 to September 18. In later September, he visited Newport News, Hampton, and Williamsburg. On September 24, he discusses the meeting of trustees of Nelson districts of York and Warwick counties and the agreements to hire a supervising industrial teachers for the colored schools and to remodel "Rising Sun" School. September 25-28, he mentions Cumberland topics: C. W. Dickinson, Jr. selling eggs; Hamilton School; Tar Wallet Club; Matilda Moseley and Kate M. Barter; and, a meeting of white and colored teachers. There are scattered notes from September 29 to October 22. In York County, October 23, he mentions "Rising Sun" graded school, Thomas Lackey, and a visit to the schools. Following the journal entries is a memorandum, "Books Read during Year."
Contents List
- Travel Diary 1911 (Box 1)
- Travel Diary 1913 (Box 1)
- Jackson Davis and the Lost World of Jim Crow Education, 2 copies (Box 1)
- "Future in Europe" (Notes by Dr. Alan Gregg on his recent trip in Europe) 1940 (Box 2)
- Genealogical Data on the Ancestors and Descendants of Jackson Davis 1998-1999 (Box 2)
- General Education Board 1940-1946 (Box 2)
- "Journal of Our Trip to Europe: A Series of Letters to Helen M. Davis..." by Jackson Davis 1926 (Box 2)
- Letters from Jackson Davis 1942-1945 (Box 2)
- Letters from Jackson Davis: News from Africa 1944-1945 (Box 2)
- Letters of Condolence for death of Jackson Davis 1947 (Box 2)
- "Observations and Impressions of South America" by Jackson Davis 1942 (Box 2)
- Photographs of Jackson Davis and others 1940-1943, n.d. (Box 2)
- Printed re Jackson Davis 1911-1947
- "Statement on Social Medicine" by Alan Gregg 1943 (Box 2)
- Travel Journal of Corinne Mansfield Davis 1935 (Box 2)
- Travel Journal kept by Jackson Davis as state agent for Negro schools for the State Board of Education 1911 (Box 2)
- Travel Journal kept by Jackson Davis as state agent for Negro schools for the State Board of Education 1913 (Box 2)
- Leather brief case personalized "Jackson Davis, Richmond, Va." n.d.
- Travel Diary 1911 (Box 1)
- Travel Diary 1913 (Box 1)
- 2 copies Lost World n.d. (Box 1)